<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The shielde and revvarde of the faithfull. Or a meditation vpon Genesis 15. chap. vers. 1. Written by Philip of Mornay Lord of Plessis-Marly and faithfully translated according to the last French copie</title>
            <author>Mornay, Philippe de, seigneur du Plessis-Marly, 1549-1623.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1620</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 57 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 41 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07775</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18154</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120356</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855555</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855555</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21050</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07775)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21050)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 584:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The shielde and revvarde of the faithfull. Or a meditation vpon Genesis 15. chap. vers. 1. Written by Philip of Mornay Lord of Plessis-Marly and faithfully translated according to the last French copie</title>
                  <author>Mornay, Philippe de, seigneur du Plessis-Marly, 1549-1623.</author>
                  <author>J. B. (John Bulteel), d. 1669.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[82] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted by T. D[awson] for Nathanaell Nevvbuery, and are to be sold at the signe of the Starre, vnder S. Peters in Cornhill, and in Pope-head Alley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1620.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Translator's dedication signed: Iohn Bulteel.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The shield and reward of the faithfull.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C¹²  D⁶ (-D6).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Genesis XV, 1 --  Meditations --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:21050:1"/>
            <p>THE SHIELDE <hi>AND</hi> Revvarde of the Faithfull.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Or a Meditation vpon</hi> Geneſis 15. <hi>Chap. Verſ.</hi> 1.</p>
            <p>Written <hi>By</hi> PHILLIP <hi>of</hi> MORNAY Lord of <hi>Pleſſis-Marly</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And faithfully tranſlated accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the laſt French Copie.</p>
            <p>LONDON Imprinted by <hi>T. D.</hi> for NA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THANAELL NEVVBERY, and are to be ſold at the ſigne of the <hi>Starre,</hi> vnder <hi>S. Peters</hi> in Corn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hill, and in <hi>Pope-head Alley.</hi> 1620.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:21050:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21050:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO THE <hi>RELI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GIOVS AND WOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie</hi> Knight Syr PEETER MANVVOODE, Grace, Mercy, and Peace, from Ieſus Chriſt.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>RIGHT WORSIPFVLL,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Lord promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vnto <hi>Abraham</hi> to bee his ſhielde and his exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing great reward; the ſame he promiſeth to euery true Iſraelite, the childe of Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham: the Creator will bee the creatures ſhielde, the King his ſubiects target, the father a buckler to his child,
<pb facs="tcp:21050:3"/>God to man both a ſhielde and a rewarde, the infinite and immortal God the por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a finite and mortall man, yea a crowne to duſt and aſhes: what better ſhield can we deſire? what greater rewarde can wee require? what greater honour, digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, or profite can wee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund or obtayne? Hee is our <hi>ſummum bonum,</hi> our ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme good, the good God who is goodneſſe it ſelfe. The worthy ſubiect of our meditation, the cheifeſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect of our contemplation, capable to take away our feare, to ſatisfie our deſire.
<pb facs="tcp:21050:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>For deſire we any thing? be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold a reward, are we afraid of any thing? beholde a ſhielde, yea a more excellent ſhielde then that of <hi>Achilles,</hi> that contained in it the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of heauen, earth, and ſea, for our ſhield is the Creator of the whole world a heauenlier ſhield, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that braſen one of <hi>Numa Pompi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius,</hi> feined to be ſent downe from heauen, for the preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of the city of Rome, for the God of heauen is our ſhielde to preſerue vs: a ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher ſhield then thoſe of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon,</hi> that were of beaten golde, a more precious and
<pb facs="tcp:21050:4"/>diuine ſhield, then <hi>Perſeus</hi> chriſtall ſhield, giuen him by <hi>Pallas,</hi> to preſerue him from that ſnaky headed <hi>Meduſa,</hi> (who turned menn into ſtones) by vertue of which ſhield he ouercame her; for by <hi>y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
               </hi> vertue of this ſhield gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vs by <hi>Pallas,</hi> that is wiſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dome it ſelfe, yea himſelfe giuen to vs as a ſhield, wee haue the victorie ouer the Deuil that old ſerpent, that ſtriues to turne our fleſhy heartes into hearts of ſtone, a better and a bigger ſhield, then that of great <hi>Goliah,</hi> how great and good ſo euer it was, it coulde not couer
<pb facs="tcp:21050:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>him all ouer, nor preſerue him from death; whereas God who is our ſhield, both couers vs, and preſerues vs. This our ſhield cannot bee peirced, wil not betray vs us that of <hi>Braſidas</hi> did, it can not be taken away from vs by the Deuill, as thoſe gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den ſhieldes of <hi>Salomon</hi> were by <hi>Shiskak</hi> King of <hi>Egypt.</hi> And therefore a ſhield wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be made much of, for if <hi>Aiax</hi> and <hi>Vliſſes</hi> ſtriued ſo much for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhield of <hi>Achilles</hi> if <hi>Epaminondas</hi> being woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to death, asked if his ſhield were whole, and reioy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ced therat, yea kiſſed it, how
<pb facs="tcp:21050:5"/>much more muſt wee ſtriue to get this ſhield, and hauing gotten it, to eſteeme it, to reioyce at it, neuer to caſt it away, rather to caſt away our weapo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s then this ſhield. It was more diſhonorable in a Romane ſouldier to fling away his ſhielde, then his ſword, his dart or ſpeare, for the which fault hee was diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graced, degraded, and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed; how much more di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhonourable, nay dangerous will it be for vs to caſt away our ſhield, by the which we are couered, which the darts of Sathan can not peirce, without the which we muſt
<pb facs="tcp:21050:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>needes periſh; nay caſt away our ſhield, and God can not be our reward; and therefore let vs take vp this ſhield, em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace it and keepe it, and as ſpiritual and Chriſtian ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers armed from top to toe with the whole armour of God, hauing on the breaſt plate of righteouſneſſe, the ſword of the Spirit, the hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met of ſaluation, the ſhield of faith, fight vnder the ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Chriſt Ieſus our cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, againſt the Deuill, the world, and the fleſh; we ſhall be able to ſtand againſt the wiles of the Deuill, and to quench all the fiery darts of
<pb facs="tcp:21050:6"/>the wicked, and ſo hauing fought a good fight, hauing finiſhed our courſe, hauing kept our faith, there is laid vp for vs a crown of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes, a crowne of glory, a crowne of life, not one of Lawrel, of braſſe, of ſiluer, or of gold, giue to Roman Conquerors, but a glorious an immortall and eternall crowne, which God the iuſt iudge ſhall giue vs at the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter day yea God himſelfe ſhal be our crowne, our glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and our life; yea ſhall bee all in all in vs.</p>
            <p>This is the Summe of that diuine meditation, which
<pb facs="tcp:21050:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>that learned diuine and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious gentleman <hi>du Pleſſis</hi> penned in the French tong, which I haue tranſlated in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Engliſh, and am bold to preſent it to your Worſhips conſideration. Of all things that moued me to offer this ſmall treatiſe to your Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip: the firſt is, your great co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinual &amp; continued affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion &amp; fauour towardes our French Church of this citie of Canterbury, the ſecond, your particular affection &amp; vndeſerued loue towardes me; the laſt though not the leaſt, your calling, as being not only a Souldier, a Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine,
<pb facs="tcp:21050:7"/>and a Knight in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of this world, but alſo a Chriſtian ſouldier and a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall Knight, fighting vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Chriſts colours, againſt your ſpirituall enemies, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing GOD both for your ſhielde and your exceeding great rewarde, ſo that you may ſay with <hi>Dauid</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord is my ſhield and my portion Imbrace therefore the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine meditation of the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour, accept the good will and affection of the tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour; make much of this ſhield, it will couer you, it it will defende you from all harmes; eſteeme much this
<pb facs="tcp:21050:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>reward, &amp; you ſhal enioy all good yea God himſelfe. I be ſeech that God, who is the ſhield and the reward of the faithfull, to be both a ſhield to preſerue you from all euill, and your rewarde both of grace here on earth, and of glory in the life to come. ⸫</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Canterbury</hi> 
                  <date>the 10. of May. 1620.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your Worſhips to <hi>command in the Lord,</hi> IOHN BVLTHEL</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:21050:8"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21050:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE SHIELD <hi>and</hi> Reward of the Faithful.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>GEN. 15.1.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>Feare not Abraham, I am thy ſhield, and thy exceeding great reward.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>BRAHAM the Father of the faithfull, left at the voyce of God his coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trey, and his parentage, the ſuperſtition of his Fathers, to follow the ſeruice of the true God. And there with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all receiued a promiſe, that within ſome ages, his poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie ſhould inherit the land
<pb facs="tcp:21050:9"/>of Canaan, where hee liued as a ſtranger. There was notwithſtandinge a ſmall proportion betweene the commaundement and the promiſe, if he had not lookt further; and the more ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable was his faith in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beying, in that the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement of leauing all was directed to his perſon, the promiſe of poſſeſſing to his poſteritie, a great way off; The commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſubiect to ſudden exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, the effect of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe deferde, not to ſome dayes but to many ages; And againe of a promiſe made to a poſteritie, that paſſeth all degrees, litle ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible when one ſeeth it not, How much leſſe to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered
<pb facs="tcp:21050:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>when the great grand-children cannot at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine vnto, nay not their great grand children. Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding he is ſnatcht away from his deareſt and neereſt friends, tranſplan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from his countrie and ſoyle, in a ſtrange ayre, a more ſtrange people; who doubts here but that the fleſh in ſo an aduantageous ſubiect did argue againſt the ſpirit, reaſon againſt faith, Sathan aſſiſted with them both, againſt Gods ſeruant toſſed and much moued in himſelfe: For what could the land of <hi>Canaan</hi> ſteade him foure hundred yeares after? Much leſſe then <hi>Eſaus</hi> red pottage when he was an hungry? and in follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="tcp:21050:10"/>this purpoſe, how many miſchiefes was hee to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter and incurre<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> what goods was he to looſe, redi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous to the fleſh contrary to reaſon, little credible to his ſoule. On the other ſide taking an other courſe, the beaten way of the world, the courſe taken by his friends, what goods might he haue gotten? what euill might hee haue eſchewed? who found to fauour his part the diſcourſe of reaſon? the deſire of the fleſh and mans will? ayming at the ſame intention the ſame contention, by the inſtinſt of Sathan, who can ſpie out his time, take his occaſions, and what better, then when the faithfull is bandied in
<pb facs="tcp:21050:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>himſelfe? God therefore in this his perplexitie appeares to him in viſion, breakes all their arguments, all his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes; <hi>Feare not Abraham,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>I am thy ſhield, and thy exceeding great reward.</hi> If thou feareſt in following my vocation thy calling to haue euils, I am to couer thee I haue wherewith to put thee vnder ſhade to ſhelter thee; If thou feareſt that thou ſhalt haue no goods, I am goodneſſe it ſelfe; and this goodneſſe how great ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer it is, is ſo good, it will guſh, and diſpearſe it ſelfe vpon thee. Few words, but which comprehends all, yea a bottomleſſe depth <hi>Feare not</hi> for it is feare it ſelfe that aſſures thee;
<pb facs="tcp:21050:11"/>the feare of <hi>Iſaac:</hi> and of <hi>Iacob</hi> that only which men muſt feare; Is thy ſpirit tempted and attempted by apprehenſion, by a feeling of euils? Behold here is a ſhield for thee; Is it aſſaulted with concupiſcence, or with the loſſe of that wee call goods? Behold here is a reward. The eternall and immortall God to a mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall man, a worme, both a reward and a ſhield: Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſo great a reward, what canſt thou deſire more? Or being vnder ſo ſure a ſhield, what canſt thou feare? And that which is ſayd to <hi>Abraham,</hi> is ſayd to his ſeede, to the Church in generall, the lawfull race of <hi>Abraham:</hi> in particular to
<pb facs="tcp:21050:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>euery Iſraelite, to all the faithfull: for ſeeſt thou O <hi>Iſrael</hi> the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> behind thee, the mountaines at thy ſides, the ſea before thine eyes?<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 14.13.</note> 
               <hi>Feare ye not ſtand ſtill and ſee the Saluation of the Lord, which hee will ſhew to you to day.</hi> Moreouer doeſt thou ſee the thunderings and the lightenings, and the mountaine ſmoking,<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.20.</note> 
               <hi>Feare not, for God is come to proue you, and that his feare may be before your faces, that yee ſinne not.</hi> Wert thou but a worme before thine enemies, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible and diſdained by them, abiect and baſe to thy ſelfe;<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſaiah.</hi> 41.8.10.13.19</note> 
               <hi>Feare not Iſrael, my ſeruant, for I am with thee; Feare not thou worme Iacob, I will helpe thee, ſayth the
<pb facs="tcp:21050:12"/>Lord and thy Redeemer, the holy one of Iſrael.</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke.</hi> 12.32.</note> 
               <hi>Feare not little flocke, for it is your Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers good pleaſure, to giue you the kingdome.</hi> Yea though thou wert alone, theſe words belong to euery one let euery one take it as ſayd vnto himſelfe. For <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith for all the faithfull, yea in the name of euery one.<note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 3.6.</note> 
               <hi>I will not bee afraid of ten thouſand of people that doe ſet themſelues againſt mee round about.</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 56.</note> 
               <hi>I will not feare what fleſh can doe vnto, me.</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 46.2.3.4.</note> 
               <hi>No though the earth be remoued, and though the mountaines be carried into the midſt of the ſea, though the waters there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of roare, &amp; be troubled, though the mountaines ſhake with the dwelling thereof, yea</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 23.9.</note> 
               <hi>though
<pb facs="tcp:21050:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>I walke through the valley of the ſhadowe of death, I will feare no euill.</hi> And the reaſon of this ſtrong confidence is not leſſe ſtrong, <hi>I am thy ſhield;</hi> of thee <hi>Abraham</hi> and of all thine, the ſhield of Iſraiel, and of the Church. For <hi>Moſes</hi> ſayth,<note n="i" place="margin">
                  <hi>Deuter.</hi> 33 29.</note> 
               <hi>Happy art thou O Iſrael! Who is like vnto thee O people! ſaued by the Lord, the ſhield of thy helpe, and who is the ſword of thy excellencie</hi> Happy therefore is euery faithfull man that can confidently ſay with <hi>Dauid,</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">2. <hi>Sam</hi> 22.3.</note> 
               <hi>Hee is my ſhield, and the horne of my ſaluation.</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 5.12.</note> 
               <hi>He bleſſeth the righteous, with fauour doth hee compaſſe him as with a ſhield.</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 22 31.</note> 
               <hi>Hee is a buckler to all them that truſt in him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:21050:13"/>Againe, <hi>I am thy exceeding great reward,</hi> the reward conſequently of thy ſeede, and of the Church; and not a reward only, but alſo an inheritance, for behold,<note n="n" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7.</note> 
               <hi>I will eſtabliſh my couenant be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene thee and mee, and thy ſeede after thee, for an euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Couenant, to be a God vnto thee and to thy ſeede after thee.</hi> I will be thy God and thou ſhalt be my people; Thou mine inheritance, and I thine. Thou my pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe, I thy reward, I thy partage, and <hi>Dauid</hi> apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to himſelfe, for vs this promiſe ſaith.<note n="o" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16.5.6.</note> 
               <hi>The Lord is the portion of mine inheritance, the lines are fallen vnto mee in in pleaſant places; Yea I haue a goodly heritage;</hi> Certes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb facs="tcp:21050:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>cauſe the wiſe man ſaith,<note n="p" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccleſiaſt.</hi> 11.22.</note> 
               <hi>The bleſſing of the Lord is in the reward of the Godly, that feareth God;</hi> the rather ſaith the Apoſtle, becauſe<note n="q" place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.8</note> 
               <hi>Godlineſſe is profitable vnto al things, hauing promiſe of the life that now is, and of that which is to come.</hi> Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding this exceeding a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundant reward, ſuper a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounding infinitly our ſure demerits, our pretended merits, becauſe there is no communion of vnrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe with righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, no proportion of man to God, of nothing to all, nor therfore of humane merit to this reward, of our default our extreame dry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to this infinit ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency and fullneſſe, to this
<pb facs="tcp:21050:14"/>eternall well ſprings.</p>
            <p>Now therefore <hi>feare not Abraham</hi> ſaith he, feare not Iſrael nor any Iſraelite; for the wiſe man ſaith,<note n="r" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccles.</hi> 7.18.</note> 
               <hi>He that feareth God, ſhall come forth of them all;</hi>
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccleſiaſt.</hi> 34.14.</note> 
               <hi>Hee that feareth God, will not feare at all nor be afraide, for hee is his hope.</hi> Now hope is the counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poiſon and remedy of feare, a remedy ſtronger then the euill; An infinite remedy againſt a limited euill, an aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance in the creator, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the apprehenſion of creatures. A confidence in him that hath made all the creatures, and that ſoly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone hath made them all, and that of nothing; and therefore a confidence in him that is all, and of him
<pb facs="tcp:21050:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>that is all, againſt that which is nothing. Let all the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments therefore make a hurrie together, all the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teors arme themſelues to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether againſt vs, againſt the Church; let vs ſay with <hi>Dauid,</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 46.3.4.</note> 
               <hi>Though the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters thereof roare, and be trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, though the mountaines ſhake with the ſwelling thereof; there is a riuer, the ſtreames whereof ſhall make glad the city of God.</hi> The infirmitie and baſenes of the Church, contemptible to the eyes of vaine men; a ſmal brooke in compariſon of theſe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuous torrents, the cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent of the Ocean, ſhall not ceaſe to ſubſiſt, nor omitt to ſtreame and runne on. The faithfull ſhall ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then
<pb facs="tcp:21050:15"/>and harden himſelfe a gainſt their ſtirrings, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther trembling for the wiſe man ſaith,<note n="u" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccleſiaſt.</hi> 34.16.</note> 
               <hi>God is his migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie protection and ſtrong ſtay, a defence from heat, &amp; a couer from the ſun at noone, a preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation from ſtumbling, and a helpe from falling.</hi> Yea the Lord himſelfe ſaith,<note n="x" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 43.2.</note> 
               <hi>When thou paſſeſt through the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters I will be with thee; and through the riuers, they ſhall not ouerthrow thee; when thou walkeſt through the fire, thou ſhalt not be burnt; For I am thy Sauiour.</hi> His prouidence in a word is vnto him both a counſell and a rampier, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all accidents, againſt all caſes and haps; becauſe there are no chances in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of God. Let the tirants
<pb facs="tcp:21050:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>of the world inſence them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues and rage, the people murmur, mutin, &amp; thunder; the Ila<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds &amp; the ends of the world conſpire againſt the Church; the Lord will ſpeak to the ſoules of his ſeruant,<note n="y" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 7.4.</note> 
               <hi>Feare not, neither be faint hearted, for the fierce anger of Rezin with Syria, and of the ſonne of Remaliah.</hi> It ſhall not come to paſſe, <hi>the Lord ſhall gather the hearts of the Kinges and Captaines of nations,</hi> when and as he liſteth. <hi>All the</hi>
               <note n="z" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 78.</note> 
               <hi>choler and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of man is to him, but as much ſubiect and matter of glory and fame.</hi> The nations con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpire,<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 8.12.</note> 
               <hi>Let them take coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell together and it ſhall come to naught.</hi> Let them com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>binde and band themſelues
<pb facs="tcp:21050:16"/>together, and they ſhall bee cruſht and bruiſed; onely let vs ſacrifice vnto the Lord of Hoaſts, let vs ſerue him, and let him be our feare; and not the fury of theſe mortal men,<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 51.12.</note> of theſe men of graſſe, (as the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet ſpeaketh) that cannot ſubſiſt againſt him, that hath ſtretched forth the heauens and laid the foundations of the earth; whoſe hand wee haue ſo often felt to our comfort, and his arme for our deliuerance. For ſaith the Lord<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Cha.</hi> 13.</note> 
               <hi>Where is the fury of the oppreſſour?</hi> And haſt thou not ſeene the endes of the world to tremble, my people not withſtanding haue gone their way in peace! and haſt thou not
<pb facs="tcp:21050:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſeene them fall before my face, before my ſword as duſt, before my how as ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble? Yea let the powers of the aire, the principalities of the world, the rulers of the darkeneſſe of the world the ſpirituall wickedneſſe in high places.<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.</note> 
               <hi>With whom the faithfull are to wraſtle e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery day,</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) let them come, ſhall wee yeeld our ſelues? ſhall wee faint and leeſe courage? but rather we will ſay, the Lord is with vs, what neede wee feare<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <note n="e" place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.13.</note> 
               <hi>He is faithfull, who will not ſuffer vs to be tempted aboue that we are able.</hi> He will ſtrengthen vs againſt the deuill; he hath<note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 1.</note> created all things that are in heauen and on earth, viſible and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible
<pb facs="tcp:21050:17"/>whether they bee thrones, or dominions, or principalities or powers, all things were created by him and for him, let vs bouldly ſay, and therefore for vs, and therfore for his Church Let vs therefore oppoſe the thrones and celeſtiall dominions againſt the powers of the ayre; the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of Angels againſt the legions of Sathan, againſt their malicious practiſes; the holy conduct of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels whom God cauſeth to campe about his children, to aſſiſt them in their way in all their paces, yea the moſt ſlippereſt, that they ſtumble not againſt the gates of hell, againſt the deuils that can nothing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb facs="tcp:21050:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>the faith of Chriſt, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his members, that haue no power vpon <hi>Iobs</hi> Cattle, vpon the hogges; though they roare neuer ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much, but as much as God vnbridleth them. But let vs ſay ouer and aboue, and that without exceſſe; Theſe deuils themſelues cannot be but for vs, in as much as they are for God; their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice turnes to his ſeruice, is at Gods pay and wages, and therefore at ours. For if Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than afflict <hi>Iob</hi> in his fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, in his perſon, the Lord knowes how farre and how long, and limits him; the righteouſneſſe and patience of his ſeruant ſhines and appeares the more, and his condition is the better for
<pb facs="tcp:21050:18"/>is at the laſt. If the Deuill puts in the heart of <hi>Iudas,</hi> to ſell the bloude of the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, to betray and deliuer the ſonne of God into the hands of the Iewes; let vs adore God, baniſh all feare; He is ſould but far, far from their intention, for the ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom of our ſoules, he is deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered for the remiſſion of our ſinnes; of thoſe ſinnes that cauſe the quarrell be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene God and vs; of thoſe ſinnes where with Sathan alone did preuaile, did braue it out againſt vs, and therefore to his confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; to his ruine, and that of his kingdome, on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therſide for the ſaluation of the world, &amp; of men. Dare we ſay that this feare doth
<pb facs="tcp:21050:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>aſſure vs euen againſt God, againſt his iuſtice, againſt his anger? certes we may, ſeing that in this feare, of children of wrath we are made the children of his mercies; ſeeing we may ſay vnto him with <hi>Dauid,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue O Lord the greatnes of thy power, to try the ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth vpon the children of death; we are contented with thy clemency, becauſe there is no condemnation to the true ſeede of <hi>Abraham,</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.1.</note> 
               <hi>To them</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>which are in Chriſt Ieſus.</hi> For in this <hi>Iſaac,</hi> in this alone is the true ſeede. On the other ſide make what couenant thou wilt, with all that which makes it ſelfe to be feared in the world; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb facs="tcp:21050:19"/>out this feare thou wilt feare all things: not the elements in their fury only, but euen the leaues, yea the duſt; not the armes offenſſiue, the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour and armies alone, but how great ſoeuer thou beeſt, the flies and Cater<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pillers; not onely the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipalities of the ayre, or the powers, but alſo their cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, but their infection, yea their very breath; yea that which is the leaſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, which hath the leſt po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer in the world; For ſaith the Lord,<note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 28.15 18.</note> 
               <hi>Though thou hadſt made a couenant with death and wert at agreement with hell; yet your couenant with death ſhall be diſanulled, and your agreement with death ſhall not ſtand; when the ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowing
<pb facs="tcp:21050:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſcourge ſhall paſſe through, then yee ſhall be trod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den downe by it.</hi> And they that haue caſt their eyes to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Ethiopia,</hi> that haue<note n="i" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 20.5.</note> gloried and vanted of the helpe of <hi>Egypt</hi> ſhalbe afraid and aſhamed thereof; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariwiſe, happy is hee that feares the Lord, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeues in him; For the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked tremble where there is no cauſe of flight or feare,<note n="k" place="margin">
                  <hi>Prou.</hi> 19.26.</note> 
               <hi>But in the feare of the Lord is ſtrong confidence, and his children ſhall haue a place of refuge.</hi> A Sanctuary for <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham,</hi> when <hi>Sara</hi> his wife, his fleſh, and bones, is at the diſcretion of the Philiſtin, according to the iudgement of the fleſh; there ſaith the Scriptures<note n="l" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 20.</note> 
               <hi>Sure the feare of
<pb facs="tcp:21050:20"/>God is not in this place:</hi> Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding God cauſed himſelfe to be feared there, for his ſeruant that feared him: A ſhelter for <hi>Iacob</hi> in this feare, againſt the fury of <hi>Eſau:</hi> God ſendes before him an army of Angels, changeth ouer and beſides and turnes that cruell heart to fauour him: So far forth that <hi>Saul</hi> is afraid of <hi>Dauid,</hi> that great king of a ſheep-heard: becauſe ſaith <hi>Samuel</hi> the Lord was with him. <hi>Eliſha</hi> on the other ſide be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieged in <hi>Dothan</hi> by the king of the <hi>Aſſirians,</hi> in ſtead of fearing them takes it away from others, and giues them courage.<note n="m" place="margin">2 <hi>King.</hi> 6.16.</note> 
               <hi>Feare not,</hi> (ſayth he to his ſeruant) <hi>for they that be with vs, are more then
<pb facs="tcp:21050:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>they that be with them.</hi> An army that he ſhewes him, (God opening his ſeruants eyes at his requeſt) a moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine full of horſes, and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riots of fire round about <hi>Eliſha</hi> for his ſuccour, inuiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible before to his faith, much more to his eyes; and how often is our helpe at the dore which we ſee not, from how many dangers doth God deliuer vs which we feele not.</p>
            <p>What then? is it in the power of man, of fleſh and bloud, not to feare the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures? and ſo powerfull? ſo many perils whereunto hee is ſubiect euery moment? Nay, God forbid! yea it is as little in his power as to feare God himſelfe: to
<pb facs="tcp:21050:21"/>feare God, and not to feare the creatures, ſpring from one fountaine, and that fountaine is God himſelfe; faith the gift of God, that prints in vs his feare, ought alſo to wipe out of vs all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther feare; and therefore he that bids vs, <hi>feare not,</hi> adds ſometimes, <hi>but beleeue,</hi> yea which is more, hee that bids vs beleeue and feare not, in commaunding it, workes it in vs by his word this powerfull word to create in vs theſe qualities, which we haue not; no leſſe powerfull then in ſaying, <hi>Let their be light, let the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters bring forth.</hi> This word bringes forth, cauſeth them to bring forth thoſe things that were not; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb facs="tcp:21050:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>is it ſayd, <hi>I will com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand my bleſſing vpon you;</hi> becauſe that his ſayings is a doing, his word an act, his bleſſing a good deed, a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine effect of his good will towards his children. On the other ſide, I will dread before you, to make your way plaine. I will put into the hearts of your enemies to forgoe you their place; they ſhall beate you another time in one quarter and you ſhall flie away ſeauen wayes, namely according as you ſhall feare mee, or not feare me. Becauſe it is God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, that can giue or take away this feare, in his bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings or curſes, as to create all other things. But yet
<pb facs="tcp:21050:22"/>wee muſt be well aſſured, that hee that gaue theſe qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities vnto <hi>Abraham,</hi> and to our fathers according to the ability and capacitie of their infirmity, in comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding &amp; reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mending them vnto them by mouth, giues them to vs at this time, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king them of him with hart, in the name of his welbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued (as the Apoſtle ſaith)<note n="n" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iam.</hi> 1.6.</note> 
               <hi>Aſke in faith, nothinge wauering,</hi> Our Lord him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſaith,<note n="o" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 14 <hi>&amp;</hi> 15. <hi>&amp;</hi> 16.</note> 
               <hi>Aſke my father in my name; Aſke and it ſhall be giuen you. For in this feare, there is confidence,</hi> ſaith the wiſe man. Confidence that proceeds from faith; faith that aſſures vs of Gods loue towards vs, breeds in our hearts a loue towards
<pb facs="tcp:21050:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>God. Two loues ſpringing from one fountaine, the firſt takes from vs or dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſheth in vs the feare of creatures,<note n="p" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.31</note> 
               <hi>For if God be for vs, who can be againſt vs?</hi> The ſecond, a reflection of the firſt, which giues vs his feare the feare of a Sonne to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards his father, no more of a ſlaue towards his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, nor of an offender to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards his iudge. A feare to offend his gentleneſſe, not to prouoke his anger.</p>
            <p>Now it is this faith alſo, which alone is capable in <hi>Abraham,</hi> in all the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, to take this ſhield that God preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, to take it I ſay, not by the merit of workes which it brings forth, what are they? Nor for the digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie
<pb facs="tcp:21050:23"/>that is in her; for what is infirmitie? but in the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion of his mercie, in his gratious promiſes. <hi>For I am thy ſhield,</hi> ſayth the Lord vnto <hi>Abraham,</hi> the Lord an infinite eſſence, a holineſſe not to be appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched by ſinners, a conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming fire that deuours them where is then the hand that ſupports it, yea that takes it, that can beare it but by him, take it but by himſelfe. Surely wee haue no other hand to lend, then that of faith and hee him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe giues it vs. And againe this faith hath no holde but by his promiſe, this ſhield cannot bee handled, nor welded but by faith in God, grounded on his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes.
<pb facs="tcp:21050:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>Otherwiſe who would be ſo raſh that durſt preſume to arme himſelfe with his power, or couer himſelfe with his goodnes, to ſtand and ſhelter him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe therewith and vſe it as a buckler againſt the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, againſt the creator but by himſelfe; and therefore it is ſayd that by faith <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> left his countrey, obeyed to the voice of God euen ſo farre as to offer his onely ſonne; Who<note n="r" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.</note> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt hope beeleeued in hope, kept and looked for an iſſue and poſteritie from barrenneſſe, after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards<note n="ſ" place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.</note> of a child whom hee led to death, and in fine, millions of his onely ſonne; refelling and bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb facs="tcp:21050:24"/>backe all temptations with his ſhield. But it was alſo expreſly ſayd that it was grounded on the promiſes. Behould then how <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> euery true Iſraelite, hath the Lord for his ſhield, takes hold of him by faith, keepes him by his promiſe; What neede he then feare? what? that this ſhield is not bigge enough to couer him? ſtrong enough to defend him? Why, hee couers the whole world with his ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowe, hee couers particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly his Church vnder his winge. It is not ſuch a<note n="t" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 28.20.</note> nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row couering, wherewith the Prophet threateneth vs; When wee pretend to couer ourſelues againſt him without him, againſt the
<pb facs="tcp:21050:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>Creator by a pretended a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement with the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, with death, the graue, and hell. Contrariwiſe ſaith <hi>Dauid,</hi> it is a ſhield of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, yea ſaluation it ſelfe; hee that retires himſelfe thereto<note n="u" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 91.</note> 
               <hi>Shall abide vnder the ſhadow of the Almighty;</hi> is couered with his feathers; his truth, the faithfulneſſe of his promiſes ſerues him in ſteade of a Target, though a cloud of arrowes ſhould fall vpon him, it cannot hurt him, <hi>no plague</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>ſhall come nigh thy dwelling</hi> much leſſe nigh his perſon. Doth the world beate vs with loſſes and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities?<note n="i" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 5.21 22.</note> 
               <hi>Thou ſhalt not bee afraide of deſtruction when it commeth, at deſtruction and
<pb facs="tcp:21050:25"/>famine thou ſhalt laugh.</hi> Will he pierce vs with the diſfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours of calumnities? <hi>Thou ſhalt be hid from the ſcourge of the tongue,</hi> how piercing, how venemous ſoeuer it be. Doth hee threaten vs with death? doth he offer it vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our view?<note n="y" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 91.7.</note> 
               <hi>A thouſand ſhall fall at thy ſide, and tenne thouſand at thy right hand.</hi> For all that it ſhal not come nigh thee, hee cannot haſten it a minute, yea euen then when he throwes his dart at our hearts, when he thinkes he hath found the default and weakeſt part of this ſhield in our infirmitie. But rather it ſhalbe our life, and truely life. It is then properly that we ſhall braue it.<note n="z" place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.</note> 
               <hi>O death where is thy ſting?
<pb facs="tcp:21050:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>Where is thy victory?</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 19.26</note> 
               <hi>For I know</hi> (ſaith <hi>Iob</hi>) <hi>that in this my fleſh</hi> (which thou thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt thou haſt killed) <hi>ſhall I ſee God;</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.43.</note> 
               <hi>I know</hi> (ſayth the Apoſtle) <hi>that that which is ſowne in diſhonour and weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ſhalbe raiſed in glory and power.</hi> So then doth the faithfull ſuffer? Is the Church aſſaulted in her bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, in her members? Let vs beware of all things, that we fling not away our ſhield. Let vs rather forgoe our weapons. If Chriſt had not beene buried. layd in the graue, couered with a ſtone; thou hadſt not beleeued hee could haue raiſed himſelfe to life, how much leſſe thee? If alſo the Church were not perſecuted, thou in the
<pb facs="tcp:21050:26"/>Church; thou couldſt not know what this ſhield is worth, how much it ſteades thee. Thou couldſt not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne thine infirmity from his power. Thou wouldſt impute to the hardneſſe of thy ſkin that which thou ſholdſt attribute to her tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per; to thy nature that, that comes from his grace, to hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane prudence that which proceeds from his proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence; and therefore it behoues thee to bee often tempted, to be toucht to the quicke. And therefore the Prophet did reioyce; that he had beene chaſtiſed, that he might thereby remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber God, and know him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. And at leaſt haue we this ſure comfort in our af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions
<pb facs="tcp:21050:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>and our wounds, from whence ſoeuer they come they aime directly at this ſhield, they fall vpon this ſhield, vpon the Lord, yea vpon his owne fleſh. If we are vniuſtly perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the malice or igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of men,<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 9.</note> 
               <hi>Saul why preſecuteſt thou mee?</hi> ſayth Chriſt, he feels throughly our paines, he accepts our wounds, hee will repell them, he will auenge them, no leſſe then if they were his owne. And therefore haue wee ſeene ſo many darts blunted, ſo many wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons become dull, ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny armies to retire; the ſharpeſt points of weapons to turne &amp; retort vpon the face of the enemies, the very
<pb facs="tcp:21050:27"/>fineſt, the very ſharpeſt, the moſt finely temperd, to their owne damage. If wee are iuſtly to be chaſtiſd for our ſinnes, hee beares the puniſhment, hee caries the wounds. The eternall ſonne of God one with him,<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53.</note> 
               <hi>Surely hath borne our griefes</hi> (ſaith the Prophet) <hi>and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried our ſorrowes; hee was wounded for our tranſgreſſions, he was bruſed for our iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, for the tranſgreſſion of my people was he ſtricken ſaith the Lord.</hi> And from thence let vs hearten and harden ourſelues alſo againſt death, againſt Sathan, againſt hell. For what can we deſire and require more in a ſhield, to haue all his qualities, then to make our wounds hers,
<pb facs="tcp:21050:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>then to redeem vs, to except vs from euil, and to reuenge them, to repell them more liuelily, to make ours hers? why then doth the fleſh arme her principalities a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vs?<note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ierem.</hi> 6.1</note> 
               <hi>Doth ſhe lay hold without compaſſion on bow and ſpeare, againſt the daughter of Sion?</hi> Wee will ſay, the Lord is our ſhield; that ſhield before the which the Philiſtians fall, the walls of <hi>Iericho,</hi> yea the very earth trembleth, <hi>Then</hi> (ſayth <hi>Debo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra</hi>)<note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iudg.</hi> 5.8.</note> 
               <hi>When there was nere a ſhield or ſpeare ſeene among fortie thouſand in Iſrael;</hi> Hee hath not omitted to ſane his people. The ſhielde of the mighty (ſayth <hi>Dauid</hi>) is driuen backe, ſo calleth hee <hi>Saul,</hi> but the ſhield of the
<pb facs="tcp:21050:28"/>righteous will neuer faile; On the otherſide.<note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 47.10.</note> 
               <hi>The ſhields of the earth belong vnto God,</hi> hee rules ouer all the ſheilds of the earth; that is to ſay, all the armour and ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of the world (will they nill they) are at his payment and intertainement, and are ſworne to him. Thence commeth it to paſſe, that we haue ſo often ſeene, the Church deliuered and relea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed from the armies of the <hi>Syrians,</hi> by the armies of <hi>Egypt;</hi> from the <hi>Aſſyrians</hi> by them of <hi>Perſia;</hi> from the <hi>Perſians</hi> by the armies of the <hi>Grecians;</hi> thoſe bended with all their powers to his ruine; theſe notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding hauing not the leſt thought, that tended to his
<pb facs="tcp:21050:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>deliuerance; the Church al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo often raiſed from whence and by whom one thought ſhe ſhould bee oppreſſed; then triumphing when one thought they ſhould haue led him in triumph; and the Lord of Hoaſts, (ſayth the Prophet) did that; the Lord (ſayth <hi>Dauid</hi>) vnto whom belong al the ſhields of the earth, on whom de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend all the Monarchies: whence it commeth to paſſe, that vnder this ſhield the Church hath paſſed ouer all the ages and ſeaſons and ſhall without doubt ſhut vp the laſt age; although that all the Monarchies, one after another in the emulation and deſpight one of the other, haue trod her
<pb facs="tcp:21050:29"/>vnder foote. They one the otherſide, all of them diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comfited the one by the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, without leauing any trace or marke after them but what was for the glorie of God. Of God (ſayth <hi>Moſes</hi>) that carieth his Iſrael vnder his wing, as the Eagle her young ones; of God on the otherſide, who in fauour of his Iſrael, and hy his iuſt iudgement, withdraweth his protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from other people. The powers of the ayre doe they reuy at hir on the earth, &amp; doe they thinke they can doe more againſt her? Haue they cauſed our fleſh to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uolte againſt our ſpirit, to make vs ſin, drawne in our conſciences to conuict vs,
<pb facs="tcp:21050:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>kindled as they ſuppoſe, Gods wrath to confound vs; ranked in a word, all our ſinnes in battaillion before our eyes, to make vs trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, to terifie vs, to make vs deſpaire of his mercy, to giue vs ouer to Sathan as a pray; Let vs here take hold, and the more firmely on the ſhield of faith, on this ſhield (ſaith <hi>Paul</hi>)<note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>Epeſeſ.</hi> 6.</note> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with we ouercome in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate the principalities, the powers, the ſpirituall wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ednes in high places; wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we may quench the fiery darts of the wicked. Tell him, I haue beene indeede<note n="i" place="margin">1 <hi>Tim</hi> 1.1</note> an idolater, a blaſphemer, a perſecuter, an oppreſſour, and much more! but I ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained mercy, and the grace
<pb facs="tcp:21050:30"/>of our Lord was exceeding abundant towards mee in Chriſt Ieſus; and this Chriſt the ſon of God hath chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged my ſinnes, hath beene made ſinne for mee, and I haue put on Chriſt, &amp; I liue in Chriſt, and Chriſt in me. If then thou canſt nothing againſt Chriſt, againſt my head, neither canſt thou a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me. Theſe ſinnes of mine how enormous ſoeuer they be, concerne mee no more, neither then the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment. As little ſhall thy darts beare againſt mee or hurt mee, furniſhed with Chriſt, armed with Chriſt; no nor againſt Chriſt nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Chriſt that ſtrong man who hath long agoe bound thee, caſt thee into the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomleſſe
<pb facs="tcp:21050:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>pit; Chriſt the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed ſeede to his Church, and vnto all the faithfull, who hath heretofore brui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed thy head; And thou canſt not with all thy rage doe more without danger then pricke our heele. Final<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, doth the almightie hee preſent himſelfe in his iuſtice, in his anger? A con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuming fire; let not the Chriſtian feare, though hee were of ſtraw; Lord will hee ſay permitt that duſt and aſhes ſpeake to thee? Thou art exceeding iuſt, the moſt iuſt; So that the ſinner cannot ſubſiſt in thy iuſtice. But good God, haſt thou not armed vs with the righteouſneſſe of thy Sonne? and hath hee not
<pb facs="tcp:21050:31"/>beene made ſinne for vs? and hath hee not beene made vnto vs righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and ſanctification? Thou ſitteſt indeede in iudgement; and thy iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is a conſuming<note n="k" place="margin">
                  <hi>Malac.</hi> 3.2</note> fire, is like a refiners fire; the ſtraw or the ſtubble ſhall they not bee parcht and burnt on a ſudden? But O God! are not wee founded and grounded vpon thy Sonne Ieſus Chriſt, towe and ſtubble that wee are?<note n="l" place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.</note> And ſhall wee not then be preſerued from this fire? And againſt the fire of thine ire and wrath, are not wee bedewed and ſprinckled with the water of thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies? bathed in the bloud of of thy Lambe? in this liuing
<pb facs="tcp:21050:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſpring ſpringing to life e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall? Certes thou art great, O Lord, thy iuſtice infinite; But thy Sonne, ſayth he not, <hi>I and my father are one;</hi> and then is hee not equall to thee, infinit to an infinite, his obedience to thy iuſtice? Therfore march wee O God by thy mercie, vnder the obedience of thy Sonne; vnder this ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience we will not decline from thy iudgement, wee will no more cry out away with thy iuſtice; but rather, and that aloud, let thy iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment come, thy iuſtice ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riue; thy iudgement,<note n="m" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.</note> 
               <hi>For there is no condemnation to them that are in Chriſt Ieſus, Who ſhall lay any thing to the charge of Gods elect; It is God
<pb facs="tcp:21050:32"/>that iuſtifieth.</hi> Thy iuſtice, for it can doe nothing but iuſtice vnto his righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and his righteouſneſſe is ours. Thou wilt glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie him, O Lord, for his righteouſneſſe, for he hath deſerued it; Yea with that ſame glory that he had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he came into the world and hee had it already, and neuer left it; and therefore hath it doubly; the laſt ſhalt be ours,<note n="n" place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.8</note> 
               <hi>A crowne of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>is layde vp for me, which the Lord the righteous iudge ſhall giue me at that day,</hi> (in that great day otherwiſe ſo ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible and dreadfull) <hi>and not to me onely, but vnto them alſo that loue his appearing.</hi> Certes whether it bee in
<pb facs="tcp:21050:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>grace, or in glory.</p>
            <p>And it is that alſo that the Lord addes vnto <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham I am thy exceeing great reward.</hi> For, it ſufficeth him not, to couer vs from harm; mans deſire ſtoppes not there, much leſſe Gods goodneſſe; hee will alſo fill vs vp with goodneſſe. It pleaſed him to bee our Shield againſt the euill of this world, &amp; of the world to come. In like proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is he our Reward; A re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward heere beneath, a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward aboue: In things of this preſent life neuer to forſake vs: In things of the life to come giuing himſelfe to vs. But in the one and in the other, by his grace a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone; for what coulde hee
<pb facs="tcp:21050:33"/>without forgiuing? Now, what a large fielde hath the Chriſtian heere to meditate vpon theſe hie mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries? He knoweth &amp; ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgeth nought in himſelfe but wickedneſſe, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen from his conception, in his conception nought but ſinne. He cannot be ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant, that the wages of ſinne is death, and of a ſin that is infinite, an infinit puniſhment; againſt a God eternall, an eternall death. Where is then the reward? or rather, where is not the puniſhment? And where is the ouer-weening preſumer that askes a Reward? that thinkes not he hath gained much to be quitt of the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment? but the Lorde
<pb facs="tcp:21050:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſayth to him in mercy, <hi>I am thy Reward,</hi> in lieu of the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment that is due vnto thee: A man conceiued in ſinne, a ſtranger vnto my law, as all others are. And I will not onely giue thee a reward, but giue my ſelfe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to thee, as an infinite re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde, not due to thy me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites, mauger thy demerits. For, by what law can the ſlaue purchaſe his maſter by his ſeruice, or the ſubiect his prince? to haue him for a reward, to make him his owne, to poſſeſſe him as an inheritance? much leſſe the creature his Creator: vnleſſe certes (ſayth the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle) it be by the law of faith, by pure grace. So that we haue him as a rewarde,
<pb facs="tcp:21050:34"/>with the ſame right and ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle as wee haue him for a ſhield, by faith grounded on his promiſe. And not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding <hi>a Reward</hi> ſaith the Lord, and therfore due; but how due? It is due vnto thee, for I haue promiſed it thee, thou haſt not deſerud it, I owe it vnto my ſelfe. It is due to thee, I owe it to my Sonne, bought with his bloud, and I haue giuen him thee, yea, his bloud for thee, and therefore due to thy ſelfe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I am</hi> therefore ſayth the Lord to Abraham <hi>thy Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward;</hi> But heere fleſh and bloud are not contented therewith, cannot attaine vnto it; and therefore <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> ſayth, <hi>Lord God,
<pb facs="tcp:21050:34" rendition="simple:additions"/>what wilt thou giue me, ſeeing I goe childleſſe?</hi> So little can eternall and heauenly hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pines pierce into our ſoules except it hath firſt entred into our hearts; Yea but when I ſay vnto thee <hi>I am thy Reward;</hi> I comprehend all, euen that All my ſelfe; for wilt thou haue poſterity (ſaith hee)? <hi>Looke now to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Heauen, and tell the ſtarres, if thou be able to num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber them, ſo ſhall thy ſeede be,</hi> and notwithſtanding hee had but one ſonne: VVilt thou haue goods? <hi>I giue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee, and vnto thy ſeede af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter thee this land for an euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting poſſeſſion,</hi> and yet muſt he buy his ſepulchre; and wilt thou aſſure them for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, the Lord makes a coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant
<pb facs="tcp:21050:35"/>with thee; notwith. ſtanding thy poſterity ſerues many ages after: now to what end was this but onely to raiſe him vp from the creatures to the Grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, to tell him plainely, if theſe earthly things ſeemes to thee a rewarde worthy for thee that art but duſt, it is not a preſent worthy of God that gives it thee the euerlaſting God cannot give unto his children wor thily but euerlaſting things. And not withſtanding leaſt thou ſhouldſt bee diſcoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, I am in ſuch wiſe thy reward aboue, as that I ceaſe not to be it heere beneath, for,<note n="o" place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.8,</note> 
               <hi>godlineſſe</hi> my true ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, <hi>hath the promiſe of the Life that now is, and of that
<pb facs="tcp:21050:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>which is to come.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore doe we ſee him bleſtin his family, abound in his houſhold buſineſſe, rule a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt ſtrangers, reueren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced and honoured of idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters? I am ſo in this life a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, as I ceaſe not to be it in their death, and then ſo much the more; not as the maſters of this world, their ſeruants dead, dead their ſeruices: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore doe we reade ſo often, <hi>The God of Abraham, of Iſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ac, and of Iacob; For the loue of my ſernant Abraham:</hi> for, the promiſe of the eternall. God is eternall, ſuruiues his ſeruants and their ſeruices, Therefore the Apoſtle ſaid, p. <hi>To me to line is Chriſt, to die</hi>
               <note n="p" place="margin">
                  <hi>Philip</hi> 1.</note> 
               <hi>to die is gaine; ſo alſo Chriſt ſhall be
<pb facs="tcp:21050:36"/>magnified in my body, whether it be by life or by death.</hi> In a word, ſerue thou in this life according to thy calling, according to mine, who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer it bee, howſoeuer froward hee be to thee, be not diſmayed, thou loſeſt not thy paines.<note n="q" place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6. <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.</note> The ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant ſerues his maſter with good will, the ſubject his prince; he ſerues the Lord hee doth the will of God not of men, with good will doing ſeruice as to the Lord and not to men. But let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> relie alſo on him, truſt to this reward, and not to men. For haſt thou<note n="r" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 3. <hi>&amp;</hi>32.</note> 
               <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi> ſerued an vngratefull <hi>Laban,</hi> the beſt of thy yeares in the ſcorchng heate of the Sunne by day, in the froſt
<pb facs="tcp:21050:36" rendition="simple:additions"/>by night; and the Lord hath euidently bleſt thee to his profit, it may be to thy dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage. <hi>Feare not</hi> (ſayth the Lord) <hi>For I am thy reward.</hi> Thou haſt paſſed ouer the <hi>Iordan</hi> with thy ſtaffe, and behould thou art become two bands. Haſt thou faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully ſerud a prince, or the ſtate of a kingdome; and God hath he vouchafed to worke amongſt them by thy hand; and they repay thee with co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tempt, with ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, yea with, iniuries; doe not bemoane thy ſelfe, doe not bely thy ſelf, or derogate from thy ſelfe, whatſoeuer happens thee, thou haſt ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued according to confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and not according to fauour, and not accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb facs="tcp:21050:37"/>to anger, thou haſt, ſerued the Lord thy God, and not men; <hi>The Lord is faithfull</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) is faithfull,<note n="s" place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.6.</note> 
               <hi>He that commeth to God muſt beleeue that hee is, and that he is a rewarder of them that diligently ſeeke him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That is to ſay, that it is not more true, that God is, then that it is conſequently true that his reward is with true that his reward is with him; that he is the reward of them that ſerue him, euen of thoſe that in the conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of his calling, take their condition in good part, vndergoe ioyfully all bitternes, and their charges and burdens ſcarce tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le and ſupportable for the moſt part in themſelues, leſſe for being leſſe acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged,
<pb facs="tcp:21050:37" rendition="simple:additions"/>but leaſt acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged of them, whom they ſerue; Iſrael alſo, I meane the Church, is ſhe hardly oppreſt in <hi>Egypt; Ioſephs</hi> ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uices are they there forgot, yea turned into torments and puniſhments, to make and bake brickes, to gather ſtraw, to feele the rod of the taſke-maſters, the diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the exacter, the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uere corrector? Let him not doubt but that hee ſhalbe drawne away with an out ſtretched arme, a ſtrong hand, that God ſhalbe glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified in deliuering his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, in chaſtiſing <hi>Egypt.</hi> But know alſo Iſrael, and doe not abuſe thy ſelfe that thy reward is not in this ſoyle, in the ſlime and mud of
<pb facs="tcp:21050:38"/>
               <hi>Nilus,</hi> Thou art there a ſtranger, how fertill ſoeuer it be; but thy reward is in <hi>Canaan,</hi> in the true <hi>Canaan,</hi> in the heauenly. There pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly, <hi>Shalt thou laugh at the cry of the oppreſſors,</hi> at the noiſe of people, there maiſt thou ſay aſſuredly,<note n="t" place="margin">
                  <hi>Va.</hi> 14.4.</note> 
               <hi>How hath the oppreſſour ceaſed? and what is become of the Scepter of the rulers:</hi> Yea comeſt thou thus farre, O ſeruant of God whoſoeuer thou beeſt, to receiue amongſt thine owne, amongſt his owne, hard handling yea euen death for thy paines and pay; Thy pay and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward for that thou haſt aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted them with counſell in their perplexities, with aide in their aduerſiries
<pb facs="tcp:21050:38" rendition="simple:additions"/>thou haſt made no recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of thy life, of thy dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, of all that man ciuily eſteemes moſt; and that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe many times they ſhall want an onyon or melon, or ſomeſauce of <hi>Egypt;</hi> not neceſſary things but things ſuperfluous; yeeld not vnto them, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>fly bend and harden thy ſelfe againſt them, to doe them good. For how often haue they murmured againſt <hi>Moſes:</hi> and haue not they knocked downe the Prophets, and did they euer reuerence them but when they were dead? and would they not ſtone our Sauiour: and haue not they forgot the Lord their poſſeſſion? Yea how often haue they kicked
<pb facs="tcp:21050:39"/>againſt him? Now who art thou then, what are thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uices, that thou expreſſeſt either leſſe, or better? and the greater they ſhalbe, ſeeſt thou not that proportion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly they are often followed with enuie, yea with hatred and reproach yea though the Lord ſhould ſay vnto thee, as he ſaid vnto <hi>Moſes</hi>
               <note n="u" place="margin">
                  <hi>Numb.</hi> 14.</note> 
               <hi>I will ſmite this people with the peſtilence; and diſinherite them; and will make of thee a greater nation, and mightier then they.</hi> Doe not conſent vnto their euil, their puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, no not vnto thine owne good; ſay rather, Lord what will the <hi>Egyptians</hi> ſay, <hi>The Lord was not able to bring this people into the land which he ſware vnto them, therefore
<pb facs="tcp:21050:39" rendition="simple:additions"/>he hath ſtane them in the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe Pardon I beſeech thee the iniquitie of this people, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording vnto the greatneſſe of thy mercie, and as thou haſt for given this people from Egypt even vntill now,</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 23.34.</note> 
               <hi>For give them father</hi> ſaid our Lord Chriſt, <hi>For they know not what they doe,</hi> Yea euen bee willing to ſacrifice thy ſelfe for them, to make thy ſeife an <hi>anathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma,</hi> acc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rſed; becauſe Certes thy reward is not here, nor of here beneath, it is from a boue and it is there alſo and therefore be not offended, if the wicked doe proſper. It belonges to the men of this world to ſeeke it here on earth, to expect it of men. Contrarie wiſe it is ſaid vnto vs<note n="y" place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 3.11.12.</note> 
               <hi>Bleſſed are yee,
<pb facs="tcp:21050:40"/>when men ſhall reuile you, and perſecute you, and ſhall ſay all manner of euill againſt you falſely for my name ſake; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce and bee exceeding glad, for great is your reward in heauen;</hi> Great in it ſelfe, and indeede what is there great but God? No leſſe great in regard of the faithfull. For<note n="z" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 8.4.</note> 
               <hi>What is man that thou art mindfull of him, and the Sonne of man that thou viſiteſt him?</hi> And therefore it is added <hi>very great,</hi> or <hi>exceeding great</hi> in him and of him, for God is all ſufficient to himſelfe, and therfore ſuper abounds vpon all creatures, &amp; of his fulneſſe haue they all recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued; but ſo much the more in vs, for the due wages of all men was death, and what
<pb facs="tcp:21050:40" rendition="simple:additions"/>haue the beſt men of all but that which they haue recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued? and is it not then grace vpon grace and not ſalary: and beſides, what can wee doe that can oblige God, or make him beholden vnto vs, ſeing that<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16.</note> 
               <hi>Our goodneſſe</hi> (ſayth the Pſalmiſt) <hi>exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth not to him,</hi> For what can wee ſuffer, that is wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy him: Seeing ſayth the Apoſtle that<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rim.</hi> 8.18.</note> 
               <hi>The ſufferings of this preſent time, are not worthy to bee compared with the glorie, which ſhalbe reuea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in vs.</hi> But Certes, <hi>where</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.20.21.</note> 
               <hi>ſinne abounded, grace did much more abounde; that as ſinne hath reigned vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to death, euen ſo might grace reigne through righteouſneſſe, vnto eternall life, by Ieſus
<pb facs="tcp:21050:41"/>Chriſt our Lord.</hi> Grace veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly moſt abounding drawn from the depth of the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of the mercies of God our father, reconciling his elected and choſen in his Sonne; the ſeede of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> according to the fleſh, but the ioy of <hi>Abraham</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the promiſe, in whom he hath called vs, iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified, ſanctified, and glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied vs; In whom, and for whoſe ſake he will be heere of meere good will our Shield; in heauen aboue, freely our Reward: And therefore again and again, feare not Iſrael, feare not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny true Iſraelite; for<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 11.2.</note> 
               <hi>Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed is the man</hi> (ſayth the Pſalmiſt) <hi>that feareth the Lord, he ſhall not be affrayde
<pb facs="tcp:21050:41" rendition="simple:additions"/>of euill tydings;</hi> the euill al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways weaker then good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; the goodneſſe it ſelfe camping alwayes about him, camping for him, he ſhall be alwayes (ſayth he) enuironed with all kind of bleſſings; he ſhall abound in them, becauſe he ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy and poſſeſſe from this very time forward here on earth, this good thing in hope; aſſured fully to enioy it in Heauen aboue in the glory of the Father.</p>
            <p>To whom, with the Son, and the holy Ghoſt, be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed all honour, glory, power, and dominion for euer and euer, Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
